<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-07T15:44:08+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">WY Chow Lab</title><subtitle>We use solid-state NMR spectroscopy to bring new insight to biomolecules in the extracellular matrix that are relevant to human health and disease. We are based at the University of Warwick, UK.</subtitle><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><entry><title type="html">In2science summer placement</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/08/22/in2science" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In2science summer placement" /><published>2022-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/08/22/in2science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/08/22/in2science">&lt;p&gt;We hosted Reena, Hattie, Julia, and Shifa, who are all Year 12 students from local schools, as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://in2scienceuk.org/&quot;&gt;in2science UK&lt;/a&gt;. The placement took place from 15 to 19 August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in2science---what-is-it-about&quot;&gt;In2science - what is it about?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a summer programme for year 12 students to gain insight into STEM careers and research. There is a wider participation element, as students are selected based on criteria that can indicate a disadvantaged background, and are all from non-fee paying and non-selective state-maintained schools. A further requirement is that the students should be studying at least one STEM A-level/BTEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After applying to the scheme in April, I found out in June that I had been matched, and hosted four students for a week in August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-are-the-students&quot;&gt;Who are the students?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I volunteered to host four year 12 students and was matched with Reena, Hattie, Julia, and Shifa. Two of them are from schoolsaround Coventry, and two from the outskirts of Birmingham. There is a decent spread of interests: two are interested in physics at degree level, while two others are more interested in chemistry. In addition, most expressed an interest in seeing some biological research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the students are taking 3 STEM A-levels, but with a spread in subjects including: Physics, Chemistry, Biology, Maths, Further Maths, and Psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-you-do-during-the-placement-as-a-host&quot;&gt;What did you do during the placement as a host?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent ~25% of the time on solid-state NMR of biological materials, which is my research area. For the hands-on part in the lab, we were fortunate to get a few hours on the GHz spectrometer of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/physics/research/condensedmatt/nmr/850/&quot;&gt;national high-field solid-state NMR facility&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to the facility manager Trent Franks. Not all of it was in the lab – quite a lot of time was spent describing the instrumentation and basic mechanisms, linking it to current levels of knowledge. Since the students have a broad range of interests, I arranged tours/lab visits to different departments and research technology platforms (RTPs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/physics/&quot;&gt;physics department&lt;/a&gt; tour was led by Ryan Williams and Daisy Ashworth, with a tour of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/physics/research/condensedmatt/x-ray/&quot;&gt;X-ray facility&lt;/a&gt; from David Walker; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/chemistry/&quot;&gt;chemistry department&lt;/a&gt; tour was led by Dan Lester of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/services/ris/impactinnovation/impact/warwick-scientific-services/polymercharacterisation&quot;&gt;polymer RTP&lt;/a&gt;; and the visit to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mechanochemistry.org/&quot;&gt;CMCB lab&lt;/a&gt;, part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/med&quot;&gt;medical school&lt;/a&gt;, was led by Sabeeha Malek, a PhD student of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/cross_fac/mibtp/&quot;&gt;MIBTP&lt;/a&gt;. We also toured the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/services/library/&quot;&gt;library&lt;/a&gt;, kindly hosted by Kim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, I planned some sessions where we worked on a CV or a personal statement, which provided opportunities for the students to ask questions and reflect on what they have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Twitter thread describing the day-to-day activities can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Bit of a belated tweet, but very pleased to welcome our Year 12 students from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/in2scienceUK?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@in2scienceUK&lt;/a&gt; who are spending this week in a work placement hosted by me at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/warwickuni?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@warwickuni&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WarwickPhysics?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@WarwickPhysics&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/in2sci22?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#in2sci22&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/in2science?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#in2science&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/1DF6B1KAyC&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/1DF6B1KAyC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ying (they/she) (@wingyingchow) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wingyingchow/status/1559961244769157123?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 17, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-you-gain-from-the-placement&quot;&gt;What did you gain from the placement?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a fairly recent starter in Warwick Physics, it was a good opportunity to meet more people in the department and around the university. Moreover, I have spent most of the last decade working as a postdoc in research institutes and felt rather out of date with current A level students in the UK, so hosting the students has actually also boosted my confidence in undergraduate teaching. Finally, it was stimulating to discuss all areas of science with the students, and to hear what inspired them most during the week. From seeing their first review article to writing their CV in LaTeX, hopefully this week will equip them with skills and confidence that lead to a succesful application to study science at degree level and eventually, a fulfilling career in science or related fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-was-difficult-about-the-placement&quot;&gt;What was difficult about the placement?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding relevant problems that can be explained properly without an A-level in maths.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding ways to talk about nuclear spin without using all the background of quantum mechanics!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When planning the activities, it felt like I didn’t plan enough things to do. Once the placement started, it felt like we don’t have enough time!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With four students, there are a considerable breadth of interest. It felt hard to plan activities that would be enjoyed by everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-the-focus-on-social-mobility-and-diversity&quot;&gt;Why the focus on social mobility and diversity?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is increasing realisation that the UK has one of the most unequal societies among similar countries in Europe and western democracies. This is reflected in multiple ways, such as income and regional disparities, but one that is most relevant to our daily work is the unequal access to higher education and entry to STEM degrees. Such inequality is partly driven by a lack of social mobility and brings several problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On a individual level, it means that people who have the aptitude and interest to enter STEM careers can end up not applying to do a STEM degree, or even to do a degree at all. This can lead to more limited career options, less satisfaction, and lower earnings over their lifetime.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nationally, the UK is not making the best use of available STEM talent. In the long-term, this will have a knock-on impact beyond the scientific/STEM community, reducing competitiveness relative to other established and emerging nations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a scientist, we believe and hope that our work and our research community will outlive us. Having an intake that is restricted to certain social classes or regions will directly impact the relevance and vibrancy of our disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, I have seen first-hand how people with interest and aptitude for STEM careers were provided with poor careers advice, leading to choices of post-16 and higher/further education that were not a good fit. It can be incredibly frustrating both for that person and others, this feeling of “if I had known”, so I hope to be able to provide a useful perspective for some year 12 students at this formative phase of their education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-sign-up-for-summer-2023&quot;&gt;How to sign up for summer 2023?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in hosting? Express your interest here: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://in2scienceuk.org/volunteers/host-apply/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in joining in2science as a student? Express your interest here: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://in2scienceuk.org/students/apply/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">We hosted Reena, Hattie, Julia, and Shifa, who are all Year 12 students from local schools, as part of in2science UK. The placement took place from 15 to 19 August.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Joining the lab through the ASCDT MSc+PhD route (UK/EU)</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/22/join-ASCDT-MSc" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joining the lab through the ASCDT MSc+PhD route (UK/EU)" /><published>2022-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/22/join-ASCDT-MSc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/22/join-ASCDT-MSc">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The deadline for this route has passed on 15 August 2022.&lt;/strong&gt; Please see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wychowlab.org/join.html&quot;&gt;join&lt;/a&gt; page for current opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in joining the lab?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fully funded studentship (for UK/EU) is available through the Warwick Centre for Doctoral Training in Analytical Science (ASCDT) Msc + PhD route for October 2022 entry. In this 4-year programme, you will take a selection of courses and pick two mini-projects for the first year, which leads to the award of a MSc in Analytical Sciences. After that, you choose one of your mini-projects to continue for a PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are offering a project titled &lt;strong&gt;Developing a solid-state NMR approach to characterise coatings and scaffolds that support mammalian cell culture&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description: Mammalian cell culture is an essential technology for biomedical research and development of personalized medicine. Cell growth and development are strongly influenced by the molecular structures present in the extracellular environment, which is provided currently by coatings, scaffolds and gels, which can show variation due to batch and preparation method. Better characterisation of the intact extracellular environment will enable the design of a new generation of materials to support mammalian cell culture for well-defined outcomes. In this mini-project, you will have the chance to learn solid-state NMR and other analytical and structural characterization techniques. You will apply these techniques to scaffolds and gels that you have prepared. Depending on interest, you may also produce samples by mammalian cell culture yourself, gaining a key skill for many areas of biotechnological industry in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other projects can be viewed at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/as/study/msc/&quot;&gt;ASCDT page for the MSc + PhD route&lt;/a&gt;. You can also find more information about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/as/about/&quot;&gt;Analytical Science Centre for Doctoral Training (ASCDT)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadline: 15 August 2022&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/CRS321/phd-studentship-warwick-centre-for-doctoral-training-in-analytical-science&quot;&gt;jobs.ac.uk listing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/analytical-science-centre-for-doctoral-training-call-for-applications/?p146060&quot;&gt;findaphd.com listing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">The deadline for this route has passed on 15 August 2022. Please see the join page for current opportunities.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Warwick Invisibleconf</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/15/Warwick-inVisibleconf" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warwick Invisibleconf" /><published>2022-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/15/Warwick-inVisibleconf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/07/15/Warwick-inVisibleconf">&lt;p&gt;Ying spoke at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/cross_fac/ias/calendar/invisible_conference/&quot;&gt;inVISIBLE&lt;/a&gt; research and diversity conference today. Her talk was titled “Using Solid-state NMR to Understand Biological Structures Essential to Multicellular Life”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying spoke at the inVISIBLE research and diversity conference today. Her talk was titled “Using Solid-state NMR to Understand Biological Structures Essential to Multicellular Life”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Start Nmr First</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/26/start-NMR-first" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start Nmr First" /><published>2022-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/26/start-NMR-first</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/26/start-NMR-first">&lt;p&gt;Ying ran her first solid-state NMR experiments at Warwick today. 千里之行，始於足下!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying ran her first solid-state NMR experiments at Warwick today. 千里之行，始於足下!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Brussels Aku Workshop</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/15/Brussels-AKU-workshop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brussels Aku Workshop" /><published>2022-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/15/Brussels-AKU-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/15/Brussels-AKU-workshop">&lt;p&gt;Ying was invited to speak at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://akusociety.org/aku-scientific-conference-may-2022-brussels/&quot;&gt;12th International Scientific Conference on AKU&lt;/a&gt;, hosted by the Alkaptonuria Society at the Vrije Universiteit Brussel (VUB). It was great to see old friends and meet new faces in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying was invited to speak at the 12th International Scientific Conference on AKU, hosted by the Alkaptonuria Society at the Vrije Universiteit Brussel (VUB). It was great to see old friends and meet new faces in Brussels.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Warwick Cmp Seminar</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/03/Warwick-CMP-seminar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warwick Cmp Seminar" /><published>2022-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/03/Warwick-CMP-seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/05/03/Warwick-CMP-seminar">&lt;p&gt;Ying spoke at the departmental &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/physics/research/condensedmatt/cmpseminar/&quot;&gt;Condensed Matter Physics seminar&lt;/a&gt;. Her talk was titled “Biological structures in the extracellular context”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying spoke at the departmental Condensed Matter Physics seminar. Her talk was titled “Biological structures in the extracellular context”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Start Appte</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/04/28/start-APPTE" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start Appte" /><published>2022-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/04/28/start-APPTE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/04/28/start-APPTE">&lt;p&gt;Ying started the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/cross_fac/academic-development/app/te/&quot;&gt;Academic and Professional Pathway for Teaching Excellence (APPTE)&lt;/a&gt; course today, a 12-month programme to develop teaching practice in higher education tailored to new academic staff at the University of Warwick.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying started the Academic and Professional Pathway for Teaching Excellence (APPTE) course today, a 12-month programme to develop teaching practice in higher education tailored to new academic staff at the University of Warwick.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Warwick Bms Seminar</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/23/Warwick-BMS-seminar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warwick Bms Seminar" /><published>2022-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/23/Warwick-BMS-seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/23/Warwick-BMS-seminar">&lt;p&gt;Ying spoke at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/med/news/eventscal?tag=BiomedicalSciences&amp;amp;view=termly&quot;&gt;Warwick Biomedical Science seminar&lt;/a&gt;. Her talk was titled “From a heavy mouse to human black cartilage: how solid-state NMR can give new insight on the extracellular matrix”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying spoke at the Warwick Biomedical Science seminar. Her talk was titled “From a heavy mouse to human black cartilage: how solid-state NMR can give new insight on the extracellular matrix”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Start</title><link href="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/01/start" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/01/start</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wychowlab.org/2022/02/01/start">&lt;p&gt;Ying started as an Assistant Professor at Warwick today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wing Ying Chow</name></author><summary type="html">Ying started as an Assistant Professor at Warwick today.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.wychowlab.org/img/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>